<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Per Hôlmich | LISportScience</title>
    <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/author/per-holmich/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/author/per-holmich/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Per Hôlmich</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© {2022-} Lasse Ishøi</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/media/icon_hucba55b6d6add185d5221e19e25d5385d_3121468_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Per Hôlmich</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/author/per-holmich/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hip adduction strength and provoked groin pain: A comparison of long-lever squeeze testing using the ForceFrame and the Copenhagen 5-Second-Squeeze test</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To compare long-lever squeeze testing using the ForceFrame and the Copenhagen 5-Second Squeeze test (5SST) for assessment of hip adduction strength and provoked groin pain in elite male soccer players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cross-sectional study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pre-season testing at facilities of a Danish professional 1st tier soccer club and academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Elite male soccer players (n ¼ 83, mean age; 16 ± 2.7 years) from U13, U14, U15, U17, U19 and senior teams cleared for full training and match participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Maximum isometric hip adduction strength (Nm/kg) and provoked groin pain (NRS 0-10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hip adduction strength was 16% lower in the ForceFrame. A Bland-Altman plot showed a systematic bias (-0.47 Nm/kg, 95% CI[-0.57; -0.38]) and lack of agreement (95% limits of agreement: -1.31;0.39 Nm/kg). In the ForceFrame, provoked groin pain was less intense (median NRS 0 [IQR: 0e1] vs. 5SST:1 [IQR: 0e3], p &amp;lt; 0.001) and reported by fewer players (NRS &amp;gt;0) (27% [n ¼ 22] vs. 5SST: 61.4% [n ¼ 51],p &amp;lt; 0.001).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The ForceFrame and the 5SST lack agreement and are not interchangeable methods. This may have implications when selecting a method for screening and detecting early groin problems in male soccer players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Femoroacetabular impingement syndrome and labral injuries: grading the evidence on diagnosis and non-operative treatment—a statement paper commissioned by the Danish Society of Sports Physical Therapy (DSSF)</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-fai-statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-fai-statement/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-fai-statement/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement summarises and appraises the evidence on diagnostic tests and clinical information, and non-operative treatment of femoroacetabular impingement (FAI) syndrome and labral injuries. We included studies based on the highest available level of evidence as judged by study design. We evaluated the certainty of evidence using the Grading of Recommendations Assessment Development and Evaluation framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found 29 studies reporting 23 clinical tests and 14 different forms of clinical information, respectively. Restricted internal hip rotation in 0° hip flexion with or without pain was best to rule in FAI syndrome (low diagnostic effectiveness; low quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: may increase post-test probability slightly), whereas no pain in Flexion Adduction Internal Rotation test or no restricted range of motion in Flexion Abduction External Rotation test compared with the unaffected side were best to rule out (very low to high diagnostic effectiveness; very low to moderate quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: very uncertain, but may reduce post-test probability slightly). No forms of clinical information were found useful for diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For treatment of FAI syndrome, 14 randomised controlled trials were found. Prescribed physiotherapy, consisting of hip strengthening, hip joint manual therapy techniques, functional activity-specific retraining and education showed a small to medium effect size compared with a combination of passive modalities, stretching and advice (very low to low quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: very uncertain, but may slightly improve outcomes). Prescribed physiotherapy was, however, inferior to hip arthroscopy (small effect size; moderate quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: hip arthroscopy probably increases outcome slightly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For both domains, the overall quality of evidence ranged from very low to moderate indicating that future research on diagnosis and treatment may alter the conclusions from this review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maximal hip muscle strength and rate of torque development 6-30 months after hip arthroscopy for femoroacetabular impingement syndrome: A cross-sectional study</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-rfd-post-op-fai/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-rfd-post-op-fai/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-rfd-post-op-fai/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Reduced sports function is often observed after hip arthroscopy for femoroacetabular impingement syndrome (FAIS). Impaired muscle strength could be reasons for this. We aimed to investigate hip muscle strength after hip arthroscopy for FAIS and its association with sports function and participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cross-sectional study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We included 45 patients (34 males; mean age: 30.6 ± 5.9years) after unilateral hip arthroscopy for FAIS (mean follow-up [range]: 19.3 [9.8–28.4] months). Maximal isometric hip muscle strength (Nm/kg) including early- (0–100 ms) and late-phase (0–200 ms) rate of torque development (Nm∗kg−1∗s−1) for adduction, abduction, flexion, and extension was measured with an externally fixated handheld dynamometer and compared between operated and non-operated hip. Associations between muscle strength and self-reported sports function and return to sport were investigated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For maximal hip muscle strength, no between-hip differences were observed for adduction, abduction, flexion, and extension (p ≥ 0.102). For rate of torque development, significantly lower values were observed for the operated hip in flexion at both 0–100 ms (mean difference: 1.58 Nm∗kg−1∗s−1, 95% CI [0.39; 2.77], p=0.01) and 0–200 ms (mean difference: 0.72 Nm∗kg−1∗s−1, 95% CI [0.09; 1.35], p=0.027). Higher maximal hip extension strength was significantly associated with greater ability to participate fully in preinjury sport at preinjury level (odds ratio: 17.71 95% CI [1.77; 177.60]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After hip arthroscopy for FAIS subjects show limited impairments in maximal and explosive hip muscle strength between operated and non-operated hip. Higher muscle strength was positively associated with higher sports function and ability to participate in sport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hamstring and Quadriceps Muscle Strength in Youth to Senior Elite Soccer: A Cross-Sectional Study Including 125 Players</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-hamstring-and-quadriceps-strength-profiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-hamstring-and-quadriceps-strength-profiles/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-hamstring-and-quadriceps-strength-profiles/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Increasing age, high quadriceps strength, and low hamstring muscle strength are associated with hamstring strain injury in soccer. The authors investigated the age-related variation in maximal hamstring and quadriceps strength in male elite soccer players from under-13 (U-13) to the senior level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A total of 125 elite soccer players were included from a Danish professional soccer club and associated youth academy (first tier; U-13, n=19; U-14, n=16; U-15, n=19; U-17, n=24; U-19, n=17; and senior, n=30). Maximal voluntary isometric force was assessed for the hamstrings at 15° knee joint angle and for the quadriceps at 60° knee joint angle (0°=full extension) using an external-fixated handheld dynamometer. Hamstring-to-quadriceps strength (H:Q) ratio and hamstring and quadriceps maximal voluntary isometric force levels were compared across age groups (U-13 to senior).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Senior players showed 18% to 26% lower H:Q ratio compared with all younger age groups (P≤0.026). Specific H:Q ratios (mean [95% confidence interval]) were as follows: senior, 0.45 (0.42–0.48); U-19, 0.61 (0.55–0.66); U-17, 0.56 (0.51–0.60); U-15, 0.59 (0.54–0.64); U-14, 0.54 (0.50–0.59); and U-13, 0.57 (0.51–0.62). Hamstring strength increased from U-13 to U-19 with a significant drop from U-19 to the senior level (P=0.048), whereas quadriceps strength increased gradually from U-13 to senior level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Elite senior soccer players demonstrate lower H:Q ratio compared with youth players, which is driven by lower hamstring strength at the senior level compared with the U-19 level combined with a higher quadriceps strength. This discrepancy in hamstring and quadriceps strength capacity may place senior-level players at increased risk of hamstring muscle strain injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Many Patients Achieve an Acceptable Symptom State After Hip Arthroscopy for Femoroacetabular Impingement Syndrome? A Cross-sectional Study Including PASS Cutoff Values for the HAGOS and iHOT-33</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-pass-after-hip-arthroscopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-pass-after-hip-arthroscopy/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-pass-after-hip-arthroscopy/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hip arthroscopy is a viable treatment for femoroacetabular impingement syndrome (FAIS). Clinically relevant improvements in hip function and pain after surgery are often reported, but it is less clear how many patients achieve an acceptable symptom state (Patient Acceptable Symptom State [PASS]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To investigate the proportion of patients who achieved a PASS 12 to 24 months after hip arthroscopy and to determine the cutoff scores of the 2 recommended and valid patient-reported outcome measures (the subscales of the Copenhagen Hip and Groin Outcome Score [HAGOS] and the International Hip Outcome Tool—33 [iHOT-33]) for which patients are most likely to achieve PASS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cohort study; Level of evidence, 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Eligible study patients were identified in the Danish Hip Arthroscopy Registry. An electronic questionnaire was used to collect data on PASS, HAGOS, and iHOT-33 12 to 24 months after surgery. PASS was measured using an anchor question. Receiver operating characteristic curve analyses were applied to identify the PASS cutoff values of HAGOS and iHOT-33 scores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A total of 137 individuals (mean age at surgery, 35.4 ± 9.4 years) were included in the study at a mean follow-up of 18.5 ± 3.2 months after surgery. At follow-up, 64 individuals (46.7%; 95% CI, 38.6-55.1) reported PASS. Higher HAGOS and iHOT-33 values were observed for participants who reported PASS compared with those who did not report PASS (Cohen d ≥ 1.06; P &amp;lt; .001). Cutoff scores for HAGOS subscales (42.5-82.5) and iHOT-33 (67.00) showed excellent to outstanding discriminative ability in predicting PASS (area under the curve, 0.82-0.92).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In total, 46% of individuals having hip arthroscopy for FAIS achieved PASS at 12 to 24 months of follow-up. Patients who achieved PASS had statistically significant and substantially better self-reported hip function compared with those who did not achieve PASS. Cutoff values at HAGOS subscales and iHOT-33 showed excellent to outstanding discriminative ability in predicting patients with PASS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
