<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Strength | LISportScience</title>
    <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/tag/strength/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/tag/strength/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Strength</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© {2022-} Lasse Ishøi</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/media/icon_hucba55b6d6add185d5221e19e25d5385d_3121468_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Strength</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/tag/strength/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Spike in Hip Adduction Strength in Early Adolescent Footballers: A Study of 125 Elite Male Players From Youth to Senior</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-06-01-groin-strength-from-youth-to-senior-football-players/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-06-01-groin-strength-from-youth-to-senior-football-players/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-06-01-groin-strength-from-youth-to-senior-football-players/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To investigate the differences in hip adductor and abductor muscle strength in elite male footballers from youth to senior level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We tested 125 players from the under-13-years (U13) to senior squads of a Danish male professional football club in this cross-sectional design study. Hip adductor and abductor force (in newtons), torque (in newton meters), normalized torque (in newton meters per body mass), and adduction-to-abduction ratio were measured using handheld dynamometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Between U’13 and senior level, adductor force increased by 104%, torque by 127%, and normalized torque by 21%. Abductor force increased by 78%, torque by 126%, and normalized torque by 17%. For incremental differences between age groups, significant increases were observed between the ages of U’13 to U’14 (18%–39%) and U’14 to U’15 (19%–33%) for all strength measures (P≤.021). No incremental difference was observed for adductor-to-abductor ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The large increases in hip adductor and abductor strength occurring between the ages of U’13 and U’15 offer insight into the strength capabilities and stress demands in these players, which may relate to injury vulnerability, and facilitate clinicians in selecting best-suited exercise interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hip adduction strength and provoked groin pain: A comparison of long-lever squeeze testing using the ForceFrame and the Copenhagen 5-Second-Squeeze test</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To compare long-lever squeeze testing using the ForceFrame and the Copenhagen 5-Second Squeeze test (5SST) for assessment of hip adduction strength and provoked groin pain in elite male soccer players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cross-sectional study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pre-season testing at facilities of a Danish professional 1st tier soccer club and academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Elite male soccer players (n ¼ 83, mean age; 16 ± 2.7 years) from U13, U14, U15, U17, U19 and senior teams cleared for full training and match participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Maximum isometric hip adduction strength (Nm/kg) and provoked groin pain (NRS 0-10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hip adduction strength was 16% lower in the ForceFrame. A Bland-Altman plot showed a systematic bias (-0.47 Nm/kg, 95% CI[-0.57; -0.38]) and lack of agreement (95% limits of agreement: -1.31;0.39 Nm/kg). In the ForceFrame, provoked groin pain was less intense (median NRS 0 [IQR: 0e1] vs. 5SST:1 [IQR: 0e3], p &amp;lt; 0.001) and reported by fewer players (NRS &amp;gt;0) (27% [n ¼ 22] vs. 5SST: 61.4% [n ¼ 51],p &amp;lt; 0.001).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The ForceFrame and the 5SST lack agreement and are not interchangeable methods. This may have implications when selecting a method for screening and detecting early groin problems in male soccer players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of a low-dose Copenhagen Adduction exercise intervention on adduction strength in sub-elite male footballers: a randomised controlled trial</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-low-dose-copenhagen-adduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-low-dose-copenhagen-adduction/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-low-dose-copenhagen-adduction/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Footballers with weak hip adductors are at increased risk of groin injury, and adductor strengthening has been shown to reduce this risk. However, the minimal effective dose of strength training to improve hip adductor strength and mitigate the risk of adductor problems remains unknown. The aim of this randomised controlled trial was to investigate the training and detraining effects of a low-dose Copenhagen adduction exercise (CA) intervention in sub-elite male footballers on eccentric hip adduction strength (primary outcome) and peak adductor squeeze strength (secondary outcome). Thirty-nine male footballers were randomised into two groups: The intervention group completed the CA twice weekly during six in-season weeks in addition to normal football training, while the control group continued normal football training. Strength testing was performed at weeks 0, 3, 6 (training period), and weeks 7-9 (detraining period). There was no between-group difference in eccentric strength at week 6 and 9. There was a significant group by time interaction at 6 weeks (0.52 Nm/kg, 95% CI 0.17-0.86) and 9 weeks (0.59 Nm/kg, 95% CI 0.25-0.93) at which the intervention group displayed greater adductor squeeze strength. These results suggest the low-dose CA intervention is insufficient to modify eccentric hip adduction strength but improves peak adductor squeeze strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
