<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kasper Krommes | LISportScience</title>
    <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/author/kasper-krommes/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/author/kasper-krommes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Kasper Krommes</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© {2022-} Lasse Ishøi</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/media/icon_hucba55b6d6add185d5221e19e25d5385d_3121468_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Kasper Krommes</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/author/kasper-krommes/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Spike</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2023-09-12-trial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2023-09-12-trial/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To investigate the differences in hip adductor and abductor muscle strength in elite male footballers from youth to senior level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We tested 125 players from the under-13-years (U13) to senior squads of a Danish male professional football club in this cross-sectional design study. Hip adductor and abductor force (in newtons), torque (in newton meters), normalized torque (in newton meters per body mass), and adduction-to-abduction ratio were measured using handheld dynamometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Between U’13 and senior level, adductor force increased by 104%, torque by 127%, and normalized torque by 21%. Abductor force increased by 78%, torque by 126%, and normalized torque by 17%. For incremental differences between age groups, significant increases were observed between the ages of U’13 to U’14 (18%–39%) and U’14 to U’15 (19%–33%) for all strength measures (P≤.021). No incremental difference was observed for adductor-to-abductor ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Spike in Hip Adduction Strength in Early Adolescent Footballers: A Study of 125 Elite Male Players From Youth to Senior</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-06-01-groin-strength-from-youth-to-senior-football-players/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-06-01-groin-strength-from-youth-to-senior-football-players/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-06-01-groin-strength-from-youth-to-senior-football-players/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To investigate the differences in hip adductor and abductor muscle strength in elite male footballers from youth to senior level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We tested 125 players from the under-13-years (U13) to senior squads of a Danish male professional football club in this cross-sectional design study. Hip adductor and abductor force (in newtons), torque (in newton meters), normalized torque (in newton meters per body mass), and adduction-to-abduction ratio were measured using handheld dynamometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Between U’13 and senior level, adductor force increased by 104%, torque by 127%, and normalized torque by 21%. Abductor force increased by 78%, torque by 126%, and normalized torque by 17%. For incremental differences between age groups, significant increases were observed between the ages of U’13 to U’14 (18%–39%) and U’14 to U’15 (19%–33%) for all strength measures (P≤.021). No incremental difference was observed for adductor-to-abductor ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The large increases in hip adductor and abductor strength occurring between the ages of U’13 and U’15 offer insight into the strength capabilities and stress demands in these players, which may relate to injury vulnerability, and facilitate clinicians in selecting best-suited exercise interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hip adduction strength and provoked groin pain: A comparison of long-lever squeeze testing using the ForceFrame and the Copenhagen 5-Second-Squeeze test</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-squeeze-versus-forceframe/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To compare long-lever squeeze testing using the ForceFrame and the Copenhagen 5-Second Squeeze test (5SST) for assessment of hip adduction strength and provoked groin pain in elite male soccer players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cross-sectional study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pre-season testing at facilities of a Danish professional 1st tier soccer club and academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Elite male soccer players (n ¼ 83, mean age; 16 ± 2.7 years) from U13, U14, U15, U17, U19 and senior teams cleared for full training and match participation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main outcome measures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Maximum isometric hip adduction strength (Nm/kg) and provoked groin pain (NRS 0-10).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hip adduction strength was 16% lower in the ForceFrame. A Bland-Altman plot showed a systematic bias (-0.47 Nm/kg, 95% CI[-0.57; -0.38]) and lack of agreement (95% limits of agreement: -1.31;0.39 Nm/kg). In the ForceFrame, provoked groin pain was less intense (median NRS 0 [IQR: 0e1] vs. 5SST:1 [IQR: 0e3], p &amp;lt; 0.001) and reported by fewer players (NRS &amp;gt;0) (27% [n ¼ 22] vs. 5SST: 61.4% [n ¼ 51],p &amp;lt; 0.001).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The ForceFrame and the 5SST lack agreement and are not interchangeable methods. This may have implications when selecting a method for screening and detecting early groin problems in male soccer players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Femoroacetabular impingement syndrome and labral injuries: grading the evidence on diagnosis and non-operative treatment—a statement paper commissioned by the Danish Society of Sports Physical Therapy (DSSF)</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-fai-statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-fai-statement/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-fai-statement/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement summarises and appraises the evidence on diagnostic tests and clinical information, and non-operative treatment of femoroacetabular impingement (FAI) syndrome and labral injuries. We included studies based on the highest available level of evidence as judged by study design. We evaluated the certainty of evidence using the Grading of Recommendations Assessment Development and Evaluation framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found 29 studies reporting 23 clinical tests and 14 different forms of clinical information, respectively. Restricted internal hip rotation in 0° hip flexion with or without pain was best to rule in FAI syndrome (low diagnostic effectiveness; low quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: may increase post-test probability slightly), whereas no pain in Flexion Adduction Internal Rotation test or no restricted range of motion in Flexion Abduction External Rotation test compared with the unaffected side were best to rule out (very low to high diagnostic effectiveness; very low to moderate quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: very uncertain, but may reduce post-test probability slightly). No forms of clinical information were found useful for diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For treatment of FAI syndrome, 14 randomised controlled trials were found. Prescribed physiotherapy, consisting of hip strengthening, hip joint manual therapy techniques, functional activity-specific retraining and education showed a small to medium effect size compared with a combination of passive modalities, stretching and advice (very low to low quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: very uncertain, but may slightly improve outcomes). Prescribed physiotherapy was, however, inferior to hip arthroscopy (small effect size; moderate quality of evidence; interpretation of evidence: hip arthroscopy probably increases outcome slightly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For both domains, the overall quality of evidence ranged from very low to moderate indicating that future research on diagnosis and treatment may alter the conclusions from this review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hamstring and Quadriceps Muscle Strength in Youth to Senior Elite Soccer: A Cross-Sectional Study Including 125 Players</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-hamstring-and-quadriceps-strength-profiles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-hamstring-and-quadriceps-strength-profiles/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-hamstring-and-quadriceps-strength-profiles/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Increasing age, high quadriceps strength, and low hamstring muscle strength are associated with hamstring strain injury in soccer. The authors investigated the age-related variation in maximal hamstring and quadriceps strength in male elite soccer players from under-13 (U-13) to the senior level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A total of 125 elite soccer players were included from a Danish professional soccer club and associated youth academy (first tier; U-13, n=19; U-14, n=16; U-15, n=19; U-17, n=24; U-19, n=17; and senior, n=30). Maximal voluntary isometric force was assessed for the hamstrings at 15° knee joint angle and for the quadriceps at 60° knee joint angle (0°=full extension) using an external-fixated handheld dynamometer. Hamstring-to-quadriceps strength (H:Q) ratio and hamstring and quadriceps maximal voluntary isometric force levels were compared across age groups (U-13 to senior).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Senior players showed 18% to 26% lower H:Q ratio compared with all younger age groups (P≤0.026). Specific H:Q ratios (mean [95% confidence interval]) were as follows: senior, 0.45 (0.42–0.48); U-19, 0.61 (0.55–0.66); U-17, 0.56 (0.51–0.60); U-15, 0.59 (0.54–0.64); U-14, 0.54 (0.50–0.59); and U-13, 0.57 (0.51–0.62). Hamstring strength increased from U-13 to U-19 with a significant drop from U-19 to the senior level (P=0.048), whereas quadriceps strength increased gradually from U-13 to senior level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Elite senior soccer players demonstrate lower H:Q ratio compared with youth players, which is driven by lower hamstring strength at the senior level compared with the U-19 level combined with a higher quadriceps strength. This discrepancy in hamstring and quadriceps strength capacity may place senior-level players at increased risk of hamstring muscle strain injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sprint performance in football (soccer players with and without a previous hamstring strain injury: An explorative cross-sectional study</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-sprint-performance-and-previous-hamstring-injury/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-sprint-performance-and-previous-hamstring-injury/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2022-02-18-sprint-performance-and-previous-hamstring-injury/index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div id=&#34;abstract&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Hamstring strain injuries are common in many sports. Following a hamstring injury, deficits in peak and explosive strength may persist after return to sport potentially affecting sprint performance. Assessment of repeated-sprint ability is recognized as an important part of the return to sport evaluation after a hamstring injury.Purpose: This purpose of this exploratory cross-sectional study was to compare sprinting performance obtained during a repeated-sprint test between football players with and without a previous hamstring strain injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Forty-four fully active sub-elite football players, 11 with a previous hamstring strain injury during the preceding 12 months (cases; mean age, SD: 25.6 ± 4.4) and 33 demographically similar controls (mean age, SD: 23.2 ± 3.7), were included from six clubs. All players underwent a repeated-sprint test, consisting of six 30-meter maximal sprints with 90 seconds of recovery between sprints. Sprint performance was captured using high-speed video-recording and subsequently assessed by a blinded tester to calculate maximal sprint velocity, maximal horizontal force, maximal horizontal power, and mechanical effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A significant between-group difference was seen in favor of players having a previous hamstring injury over 6 sprints for maximal velocity (mean difference: 0.457 m/s, 95% CI: 0.059-0.849, p = 0.025) and mechanical effectiveness (mean difference: 0.009, 95% CI: 0.001-0.016, p = 0.020).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Repeated-sprint performance was not impaired in football players with a previous hamstring strain injury; in fact, higher mean maximal sprinting velocity and better mechanical effectiveness were found in players with compared to without a previous hamstring injury. The higher sprinting velocity, which likely increases biomechanical load on the hamstring muscles, in previously injured players may increase the risk of recurrent injuries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
