<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RCT | LISportScience</title>
    <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/tag/rct/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/tag/rct/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>RCT</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© {2022-} Lasse Ishøi</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/media/icon_hucba55b6d6add185d5221e19e25d5385d_3121468_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>RCT</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/tag/rct/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Effects of the Nordic Hamstring exercise on sprint capacity in male football players: a randomized controlled trial</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2023-09-13-effects-of-the-nordic-hamstring-exercise-on-sprint-capacity-in-male-football-players-a-randomized-controlled-trial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2023-09-13-effects-of-the-nordic-hamstring-exercise-on-sprint-capacity-in-male-football-players-a-randomized-controlled-trial/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;
This assessor-blinded, randomized controlled superiority trial investigated the efficacy of the 10-week Nordic Hamstring exercise (NHE) protocol on sprint performance in football players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;
Thirty-five amateur male players (age: 17-26 years) were randomized to a do-as-usual control group (CG; n = 17) or to 10-weeks of supervised strength training using the NHE in-season (IG; n = 18). A repeated-sprint test, consisting of 4 × 6 10 m sprints, with 15 s recovery period between sprints and 180 s between sets, was conducted to evaluate total sprint time as the primary outcome. Secondary outcomes were best 10 m sprint time (10mST) and sprint time during the last sprint (L10mST). Additionally, peak eccentric hamstring strength (ECC-PHS) and eccentric hamstring strength capacity (ECC-CAPHS) were measured during the NHE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;
Ten players were lost to follow-up, thus 25 players were analyzed (CG n = 14; IG n = 11). Between-group differences in mean changes were observed in favor of the IG for sprint performance outcomes; TST (-0.649 s, p = 0.056, d = 0.38), 10mST (-0.047 s, p = 0.005, d = 0.64) and L10mST (-0.052 s, p = 0.094, d = 0.59), and for strength outcomes; ECC-PHS (62.3 N, p = 0.006, d = 0.92), and ECC-CAPHS (951 N, p = 0.005, d = 0.95).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;
In conclusion, the NHE showed small-to-medium improvements in sprint performance and large increases in peak eccentric hamstring strength and&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large eccentric strength increase using the Copenhagen Adduction exercise in football: A randomized controlled trial</title>
      <link>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2023-09-13-large-eccentric-strength-increase-using-the-copenhagen-adduction-exercise-in-football-a-randomized-controlled-trial/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://lasseishoi.netlify.app/publication/2023-09-13-large-eccentric-strength-increase-using-the-copenhagen-adduction-exercise-in-football-a-randomized-controlled-trial/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose&lt;/strong&gt;
Hip adductor injuries are frequent in football, and players with low adductor strength appear to be at increased risk of injury. High adductor muscle activity has been shown in the Copenhagen Adduction exercise (CA); however, an associated strength gain has not been investigated. This study aims to examine the eccentric hip adduction strength (EHAD) gain using the CA in-season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methods&lt;/strong&gt;
Two U-19 sub-elite football teams, including 24 football players, were randomized to either an 8-week supervised progressive training program in addition to the usual training (intervention) or to continue training as usual (control). EHAD, eccentric hip abduction strength (EHAB), and side-bridge endurance were measured using reliable test procedures at baseline and follow-up by a blinded tester.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;
There was a significant interaction between group and time on EHAD, EHAB, and EHAD/EHAB ratio (P &amp;lt; 0.025). The intervention group demonstrated a 35.7% increase in EHAD (P &amp;lt; 0.001); a 20.3% increase in EHAB (P = 0.003), and 12.3% increase in EHAD/EHAB ratio (P = 0.019). No significant within-group differences were found in the control group (P &amp;gt; 0.335). Compliance was 91.25%, and median muscle soreness ranged from 0 to 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;
The CA implemented in-season with an 8-week progressive training program elicited a large significant increase in EHAD, EHAB, and EHAD/EHAB ratio&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
